So we've looked at the importance of decisions in life.
Now to implement this in Python and Python implements decisions and gives you the ability to make decisions
using what is called the if statement.
So let's have a look at how we can use the if statement to you.
Use make useful decisions and interesting decisions inside of Python.
If statements are a very important, fundamental part of programming constantly throughout your programming
career, you'll find that you'll be using these a lot and they really are very helpful.
Basically, what they do is they allow you to decide which path to take based on previous things that
may have happened and based on conditions that may be either true or false.
Hopefully it will make more sense to you if I give you an example.
So the basic syntax of an if statement looks like this.
So we start off with an F, we then have a variable that we want to check whether this variable is either
true or false.
So I should actually probably create that variable first, so it'll make a bit more sense.
So we have a variable.
Let's make this our age.
So let's say we are 16.
Okay.
Now we want to write a program that can tell us whether this person can drive based on their age.
So in our country their age you can drive at is 18.
So in order to check whether this age variable is old enough for the person to be able to drive.
What we are going to do is we're going to use this if statement.
So the syntax is if in the variable that we want to check, then now we want to check whether this my
age variable is less than or equal to the age limit drive in our country.
So like I said that age limit was 18.
So what you'll see is I'll put in this little, well these little symbols here.
And what these symbols mean is if my age is less then 18, then something will happen.
Okay, so basically there are a lot of different conditional operators that we can use.
So what you see here is this kind of shows you what the path and symbol is and what it means in maths,
because these symbols should be quite familiar to you.
If you've done some sort of math, you're basically grade one basically.
Um, so this one's the same.
Less than means, less than greater than is greater than.
Then we don't really have this in coding.
Instead of putting this equal sign underneath like that, we go less than or equal then same greater
than or equal to.
Then if you want to check if two variables are equal to each other, we don't use one equal sign, but
we use double like this so often.
That is another mistake uh programmers make when they're first trying to learn is they might put just
one instead of two, but we'll go over examples and give you questions where you might use these so
they all become more familiar.
And then lastly we have this one to check if something is not equal to something.
So going back to our code let's continue.
So if my age, which is this my age variable up here, is less than or equal to 18, then we want to
print something to the user.
So we're going to print let's just say sorry.
No not.
Old enough to drive.
Okay.
So let's just run this and see what it does so far.
So what our program has basically done is it's gone to this first line.
It's made my age equal to 16.
Then it's testing is this value my age which is 16 less than or equal to 18.
Yes it is.
This evaluates to true.
So it is printing.
Sorry, not old enough to drive.
Now let's change this value to a number greater than 18.
So let's just make it 19.
Okay.
As you can see, nothing happens because the program has now come in.
It's checked.
Is it less than 18?
Nope.
So it doesn't print this and it goes.
The program finishes.
Now what you may have noticed, which I didn't actually mention in the beginning, is this indentation
here.
As soon as I clicked enter on this line, it brought me to the next line.
But it left this indentation.
Now that indentation is actually very important.
Okay.
So the indentation is extremely important.
So as Sara pointed out, everything that is indented is part of the condition being true.
Now watch what happens if we remove the indentation.
So at the moment if Sara hits run we will see that.
Yep okay.
Nothing's going to happen.
So let's drop that age down so that it's below 18.
And it should print those two lines.
There it does.
Sorry not old enough to drive.
One day you will be.
That's because those two lines have been evaluated to be true.
And so they are part of that condition and they're both printed.
Now let's see what happens if we move and mess with indentation.
So let's pull that second one back.
And it still looks like well okay if my age is less than or equal to 18, 80?
Which it is.
It should do those two lines.
Well, let's have a look and see what now happens.
Okay.
It's still printing the two lines.
So we might think, well everything's fine now.
There's no problem there.
It printed the two lines just as we would expect.
Okay.
Now let's go and change the age so that it's greater than 18.
So now it shouldn't print either of those lines because a condition is not true.
But.
Oh no.
Look there.
It's printed that line.
One day you will be.
So what has happened is essentially it's checking if the age is less than 18 and if it's true, it prints
that line.
Sorry, you're not old enough.
If it's older than 18, it won't print that line, but either way, it will always print line number
four, because there is no longer part of the if condition.
So that is why it's very important that you use the indentation.
If it is not indented, it will not be considered to be part of the if condition.
So it's very important to keep that indentation.
Another reason why you want to always keep the indentation.
It helps make everything logical as your programs get longer and longer.
We spoke earlier about using comments, but also indenting helps you make sense of what's going on.
And as we'll see later, we're going to have ifs and more ifs and ifs and elses and it can get quite
involved.
So making this a bit more interesting, let's now print something if this person is older than 18.
So we're going to go if my age is greater than 18.
Okay.
We're just going to print.
Yes yes.
Okay.
So all this is now going to do is we have two if statements, which basically this one's almost well
it's doing the same sort of thing as the one before it.
But except we have now have a different condition.
So now when our program runs it's got my age equal to 19.
It's first going to check.
Okay.
Is it less than or equal to 18.
No it's not.
So ignore all this.
All this code that has been indented and go find the next code that is not indented.
Then it's going to come here.
Is it greater than 18 or.
Yes it is.
So let's see what happens.
And obviously it is going to then print this statement over here.
So you can really have as many statements as you want.
But what we'll be explaining to you later is this isn't really a very efficient way to code.
And they are much better ways to do this instead of having multiple if statements, but that we will
be looking at in our next lesson.
Yes.
So at this moment, all you got to understand is the concept of an if.
How you can have a variable, you can have a conditional operator here as we looked at the various ones.
And then as long as everything is indented, if that evaluates to true, then everything that is indented
beneath it will then be executed.
So that is our if statement.
A very powerful statement helps us make decisions and branching in our code.
And let's see where we can take this in the next lesson.